Guide to the William Sully Beebe Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Sully Beebe papers
1844-1898
MS 915
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
Largely writings on Biblical subjects and on the Indians of South and Central America to support William Sully Beebe's theory that "a great philosophical cult once occupied all the Americas, originating in Peru" and that there is a relationship between the phonetic values of their pictographs and those of the semitic languages. He also held that their legends resemble those of the Genesis cycle, which, Beebe believed, had their origin in America. Included in the papers are several letters on these subjects by Beebe to Josiah Willard Gibbs, William Dwight Whitney and Henry Clark Corgin. Also miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1893-1894, on archaeology and biblical research.
Beebe, William Sully, 1841-1898
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Sully Beebe in 1895 and Frances Dorothy Beebe in 1915.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The William Sully Beebe Papers consist largely of undated writings by Beebe on Biblical exegesis and philology, South and Central American Indian mythology and languages, and related topics. There are, in addition, four letters written by Beebe, one of which encloses a manuscript; a selection of newspaper clippings about ancient history, anthropology, and American Indians completes the collection.
The manuscripts "Biblical and Hebrew Roots" and "General Vocabulary, Maya and English" were given to Yale University in 1915 by Frances Dorothy Beebe. The remaining papers appear to have been the gift of William Sully Beebe in 1895.
Biographical / Historical
William Sully Beebe was born on February 14, 1841, in Ithica, N. Y. He attended West Point Academy, graduating in 1863. He immediately entered the army, with an appointment of Second Lieutenant of Ordnance. During the Civil War, he received honors on multiple occasions. He remained in the army until 1874, when he resigned his commission. After his resignation, he spent his time creating a theory that argued, in part, for a connection between the Biblical book of Genesis and the ancient peoples of the Americas. With the start of the Spanish-American War, Beebe reentered the army and died of yellow fever in Havana, Cuba, on October 12, 1898.
Bible -- Language, style; Indians of Central America; Indians of Mexico -- Folklore; Indians -- Languages; Maya language; Mixtec Indians; Quechua Indians; Central America; South America; Beebe, William Sully, 1841-1898
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - ALS to Josiah Willard Gibbs, enclosing ms. "Cosmic Theory of Primes"; with geometric figures and numerical equivalents of letters, 1844 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - ALS to William Dwight Whitney, 1885 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 2 ALS to Henry Clark Corgin, 1898 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings
    - Biblical topics
      - Part I: Introduction to an examination of the Bible as a treatise on creation, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Part II: Origin of Biblical proper names, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Part III: Discussion of contradictions in the Old Testament, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Part III: Discussion of Biblical allegories, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Part IV: Attempt to prove the truth of Biblical philology, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Part IV: Discussion of Assyrian characters, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Part V: The Bible as a description of benevolent design, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Biblical proper names, A-E, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Quotations from Bible and authorities on ancient history, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "Biblical and Hebrew Roots", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - American Indian topics
      - "A Native Myth," [lecture before the Rembrandt Club, Brooklyn, NY], 1883 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Notes on the Chimalpopoca Manuscript [Mexican religion and legend of creation], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Religious legends and gods of the Miztec [i.e., Mixtec] Indians, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Indian myth in English translation [fragment], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Notes on religion of the Quiche [Quecha] Indians, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - "General Vocabulary, Maya and English", undated (Box 1, Folder 19 - 20)
      - Unidentified Indian vocabulary, A-B, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Use of significant symbols to describe phenomena, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Table of contents from Analysis of Basque Legends, by Rev. Wentworth Webster, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1893-1894 (Box 2, Folder 25 - 27)